LORENZ WIMMER

PERSONAL DATA

ADDRESS: Grüngasse 11/3 wimmer.lorenz@gmail.com

1050 Vienna, Austria lorenz-wimmer

in

PHONE: +43 680 5011418 lorenz221092 • O

ABOUT ME

I'm an economist with several years of professional experience in banking and economic research. I excel in collaborative problem solving and project coordination. My passions are quantitative methods, data science and programming in R. My colleagues call me 'the data scientist of our research group'. At the moment I am advising the the Ministry of Climate Change and a workers union concerning the introduction of a new ${\rm CO}_2$ tax in Austria next year. In my free time I love to meet friends, to cook and to go running, swimming and bouldering.

EDUCATION

10/2017 - 09/2020	MSc in Economics (Mathematics Major) at Vienna University of Eco-
	nomics and Business (WU). Specialisations: Spatial Economics, Eco-
	nomics of Inequality International Economics

10/2013 - 01/2017 | BSc in Economics and Social Sciences (Economics Major) at WU.

RELEVANT WORK EXPERIENCE

Institute for Advanced Studies in Vienna. Group: Regional Science and Environmental Research. Head: Alexander Schnabl.

09/2020 - present Researcher. Project Acquisition and Management, R-Coding and Version Control Management (GitHub), Economic Modelling, Applied

Micro-Econometrics, Data Management.

09/2019 - 08/2020 | Research Assistant. Input-Output-Modelling.

Raiffeisen Bank International in Vienna. Department: Market Strategy

and Quantitative Research. Head: Valentin Hofstätter.

01/2018 - 07/2019 | Student Support. R-Coding and Data Management.

SKILLS

IT | R, ETeX, Overleaf, GitHub, MS-Office, Sentinel Hub, Bloomberg, Refinitiv Datastream.

Methods | Applied Macro-Econometrics (Bayesian), Applied Micro-Econometrics (Frequentist), Operations Research, Economic Modelling, Environmentally Ex-

tended MRIO Modelling, Spatial Econometrics (Frequentist), Risk Modelling. German (Native), English (Business fluent), Spanish (Independent User), Dan-

ish (Independent User), Italian (Basic User).

PUBLICATIONS

Languages

Articles

Gust, Sarah; Mateeva, Liliana; Plank, Kerstin; Schnabl, Alexander; Wimmer, Lorenz and Zenz, Hannes (2021). *CO2-relevante Besteuerung und Abgabenleistung der Sektoren in Österreich*. Wirtschaft & Gesellschaft Bd. 47 Nr. 2 (2021). Vienna. https://journals.akwien.at/wug/issue/view/4.

Working Papers

Gust, Sarah; Mateeva, Liliana; Plank, Kerstin; Schnabl, Alexander; Wimmer, Lorenz and Zenz, Hannes (2021). CO2-relevante Besteuerung und Abgabenleistung der Sektoren in Österreich. Arbeiterkammer Wien.

Research Reports

Weyerstrass, Klaus; Kluge, Jan; Lappöhn, Sarah; Plank, Kerstin; Schnabl, Alexander; Wimmer, Lorenz; Zenz, Hannes and Wagner, Martin (2021). *Austria's Competitiveness and its Determinants. Concepts, Developments, Relative Performance and Policy Options.* IHS Research Report. https://irihs.ihs.ac.at/id/eprint/5685/.

Gust, Sarah; Mateeva, Liliana; Plank, Kerstin; Schnabl, Alexander; Wimmer, Lorenz and Zenz, Hannes (2021). *CO2-relevante Besteuerung und Abgabenleistung der Sektoren in Österreich*. IHS Research Report. https://irihs.ihs.ac.at/id/eprint/5820/.

Berger, Johannes; Schwarzbauer, Wolfgang; Strohner, Ludwig; Schnabl, Alexander; Lappöhn, Sarah; Mateeva, Liliana; Plank, Kerstin; Wimmer, Lorenz; Baumgartner, Josef; Bierbaumer-Polly, Jürgen; Fink, Marian; Friesenbichler, Klaus; Kaniovski, Serguei; Klien, Michael; Loretz, Simon; Pitlik, Hans; Rocha-Akis, Silvia and Sinabell, Franz (2020). Ökonomische Bewertung der in der Regierungsklausur am 16. Juni 2020 vorgestellten Maßnahmen. IHS Research Report. https://irihs.ihs.ac.at/id/eprint/5431/.

Gust, Sarah; Mateeva, Liliana; Plank, Kerstin; Schnabl, Alexander and Wimmer, Lorenz (2021). *Nachhaltigkeitsberichterstattung der ÖBAG-Beteiligungen*. IHS Project Report. https://www.oebag.gv.at/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/0EBAG_NHB-AUSTRIA_DT.pdf.

Policy Briefs

Czypionka, Thomas; Schnabl, Alexander; Lappöhn, Sarah; Plank, Kerstin; Reiss, Miriam; Weyerstrass, Klaus; Wimmer, Lorenz and Zenz, Hannes. May 2020. Abschätzung der wirtschaftlichen Folgen des Ausbruchs des neuartigen Coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2). IHS Policy Brief Nr 15/2020. https://irihs.ihs.ac.at/id/eprint/5325.

Czypionka, Thomas; Schnabl, Alexander; Lappöhn, Sarah; Plank, Kerstin; Reiss, Miriam; Weyerstrass, Klaus; Wimmer, Lorenz and Zenz, Hannes. May 2020. *Abschätzung der wirtschaftlichen Folgen des Ausbruchs des neuartigen Coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2)*. IHS Policy Brief Nr 13/2020. https://irihs.ihs.ac.at/id/eprint/5314.

Czypionka, Thomas; Schnabl, Alexander; Lappöhn, Sarah; Plank, Kerstin; Reiss, Miriam; Weyerstrass, Klaus; Wimmer, Lorenz and Zenz, Hannes. April 2020. Abschätzung der wirtschaftlichen Folgen des Ausbruchs des neuartigen Coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2). IHS Policy Brief Nr 11/2020. https://irihs.ihs.ac.at/id/eprint/5309.

Czypionka, Thomas; Schnabl, Alexander; Lappöhn, Sarah; Plank, Kerstin; Reiss, Miriam; Weyerstrass, Klaus; Wimmer, Lorenz and Zenz, Hannes. April 2020. Abschätzung der wirtschaftlichen Folgen des Ausbruchs des neuartigen Coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2). IHS Policy Brief Nr 10/2020. https://irihs.ihs.ac.at/id/eprint/5303.

Czypionka, Thomas; Schnabl, Alexander; Lappöhn, Sarah; Plank, Kerstin; Reiss, Miriam; Weyerstrass, Klaus; Wimmer, Lorenz and Zenz, Hannes. April 2020. *Abschätzung der wirtschaftlichen Folgen des Ausbruchs des neuartigen Coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2)*. IHS Policy Brief Nr 9/2020. https://irihs.ihs.ac.at/id/eprint/5294.

Czypionka, Thomas; Schnabl, Alexander; Lappöhn, Sarah; Plank, Kerstin; Reiss, Miriam; Weyerstrass, Klaus; Wimmer, Lorenz and Zenz, Hannes. April 2020. *Abschätzung der wirtschaftlichen Folgen des Ausbruchs des neuartigen Coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2)*. IHS Policy Brief Nr 8/2020. https://irihs.ihs.ac.at/id/eprint/5287.

Online Articles

Lappoehn, Sarah and Wimmer, Lorenz (2021). Strukturwandel in der österreichischen Landwirtschaft. Kommunal.at. https://kommunal.at/strukturwandel-der-oesterreichischen-landwirtschaft.

Plank, Kerstin and Wimmer, Lorenz (2021). SDGs als Kompass für nachhaltige Unternehmen. ÖBAG AG. https://www.oebag.gv.at/perspektive/sdgs-als-kompass-fuer-nachhaltige-unternehmen/.

Plank, Kerstin; Schnabl, Alexander and Wimmer, Lorenz (2021). Wer soll bei einer CO2-Steuer zahlen? Arbeit&Wirtschaft Blog. https://awblog.at/wer-soll-bei-einer-co2-steuer-zahlen/.

Plank, Kerstin; Schnabl, Alexander and Wimmer, Lorenz (2021). Wer soll bei einer CO2-Steuer zahlen? IHS Blog. https://www.ihs.ac.at/publications-hub/blog/wer-soll-bei-einer-co2-steuer-zahlen/.

Other

Plank, Kerstin and Wimmer, Lorenz (2021). SDGs als Kompass für nachhaltige Unternehmen. In: ÖBAG AG Sustainability Report 2020. https://www.oebag.gv.at/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/OEBAG_NHB-AUSTRIA_DT.pdf.